<refsect1 id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para>The optional
<emphasis remap='I'>ipsec.conf</emphasis>
file
specifies most configuration and control information for the
Openswan IPsec subsystem.
(The major exception is secrets for authentication;
see
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec.secrets</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>.)
Its contents are not security-sensitive
<emphasis remap='I'>unless</emphasis>
manual keying is being done for more than just testing,
in which case the encryption/authentication keys in the
descriptions for the manually-keyed connections are very sensitive
(and those connection descriptions
are probably best kept in a separate file,
via the include facility described below).</para>

<para>The file is a text file, consisting of one or more
<emphasis remap='I'>sections</emphasis>.
White space followed by
<emphasis remap='B'>#</emphasis>
followed by anything to the end of the line
is a comment and is ignored,
as are empty lines which are not within a section.</para>

<para>A line which contains
<emphasis remap='B'>include</emphasis>
and a file name, separated by white space,
is replaced by the contents of that file,
preceded and followed by empty lines.
If the file name is not a full pathname,
it is considered to be relative to the directory containing the
including file.
Such inclusions can be nested.
Only a single filename may be supplied, and it may not contain white space,
but it may include shell wildcards (see
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>sh</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>);
for example:</para>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>include</emphasis>
<emphasis remap='B'>ipsec.*.conf</emphasis></para>

<para>The intention of the include facility is mostly to permit keeping
information on connections, or sets of connections,
separate from the main configuration file.
This permits such connection descriptions to be changed,
copied to the other security gateways involved, etc.,
without having to constantly extract them from the configuration
file and then insert them back into it.
Note also the
<emphasis remap='B'>also</emphasis>
and
<emphasis remap='B'>alsoflip</emphasis>
parameters (described below) which permit splitting a single logical section
(e.g. a connection description) into several actual sections.</para>

<para>The first significant line of the file must specify the version
of this specification that it conforms to:</para>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>version 2</emphasis></para>

<para>A section
begins with a line of the form:</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>type</emphasis>
<emphasis remap='I'>name</emphasis></para>

<para>where
<emphasis remap='I'>type</emphasis>
indicates what type of section follows, and
<emphasis remap='I'>name</emphasis>
is an arbitrary name which distinguishes the section from others
of the same type.
(Names must start with a letter and may contain only
letters, digits, periods, underscores, and hyphens.)
All subsequent non-empty lines
which begin with white space are part of the section;
comments within a section must begin with white space too.
There may be only one section of a given type with a given name.</para>

<para>Lines within the section are generally of the form</para>

<para>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<emphasis remap='I'>parameter</emphasis><emphasis remap='B'>=</emphasis><emphasis remap='I'>value</emphasis></para>

<para>(note the mandatory preceding white space).
There can be white space on either side of the
<emphasis remap='B'>=</emphasis>.
Parameter names follow the same syntax as section names,
and are specific to a section type.
Unless otherwise explicitly specified,
no parameter name may appear more than once in a section.</para>

<para>An empty
<emphasis remap='I'>value</emphasis>
stands for the system default value (if any) of the parameter,
i.e. it is roughly equivalent to omitting the parameter line entirely.
A
<emphasis remap='I'>value</emphasis>
may contain white space only if the entire
<emphasis remap='I'>value</emphasis>
is enclosed in double quotes (<emphasis remap='B'>"</emphasis>);
a
<emphasis remap='I'>value</emphasis>
cannot itself contain a double quote,
nor may it be continued across more than one line.</para>

<para>Numeric values are specified to be either an &ldquo;integer&rdquo;
(a sequence of digits) or a &ldquo;decimal number&rdquo;
(sequence of digits optionally followed by `.' and another sequence of digits).</para>

<para>There is currently one parameter which is available in any type of
section:</para>
<variablelist remap='TP'>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>also</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>the value is a section name;
the parameters of that section are appended to this section,
as if they had been written as part of it.
The specified section must exist, must follow the current one,
and must have the same section type.
(Nesting is permitted,
and there may be more than one
<emphasis remap='B'>also</emphasis>
in a single section,
although it is forbidden to append the same section more than once.)
This allows, for example, keeping the encryption keys
for a connection in a separate file
from the rest of the description, by using both an
<emphasis remap='B'>also</emphasis>
parameter and an
<emphasis remap='B'>include</emphasis>
line.
(Caution, see BUGS below for some restrictions.)</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>alsoflip</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>can be used in a
<emphasis remap='B'>conn</emphasis>
section.
It acts like an
<emphasis remap='B'>also</emphasis>
that flips the referenced section's entries left-for-right.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>Parameter names beginning with
<emphasis remap='B'>x-</emphasis>
(or
<emphasis remap='B'>X-</emphasis>,
or
<emphasis remap='B'>x_</emphasis>,
or
<emphasis remap='B'>X_</emphasis>)
are reserved for user extensions and will never be assigned meanings
by IPsec.
Parameters with such names must still observe the syntax rules
(limits on characters used in the name;
no white space in a non-quoted value;
no newlines or double quotes within the value).
All other as-yet-unused parameter names are reserved for future IPsec
improvements.</para>

<para>A section with name
<emphasis remap='B'>%default</emphasis>
specifies defaults for sections of the same type.
For each parameter in it,
any section of that type which does not have a parameter of the same name
gets a copy of the one from the
<emphasis remap='B'>%default</emphasis>
section.
There may be multiple
<emphasis remap='B'>%default</emphasis>
sections of a given type,
but only one default may be supplied for any specific parameter name,
and all
<emphasis remap='B'>%default</emphasis>
sections of a given type must precede all non-<emphasis remap='B'>%default</emphasis>
sections of that type.
<emphasis remap='B'>%default</emphasis>
sections may not contain
<emphasis remap='B'>also</emphasis>
or
<emphasis remap='B'>alsoflip</emphasis>
parameters.</para>

<para>Currently there are two types of section:
a
<emphasis remap='B'>config</emphasis>
section specifies general configuration information for IPsec,
while a
<emphasis remap='B'>conn</emphasis>
section specifies an IPsec connection.</para>
</refsect1>

